Researchers are building organoids that
are capable of physical sensation. Yes,
the tiny human brains that you can grow
in a literal jar if you want to. They're
hooking them up to a spinal cord and
giving them a nervous system. Now, in
case you're new to this topic, yes,
those are tiny human brains. You can
take a stem cell and you can grow it
into a miniature version of a human
brain. Clearly, it's not going to have
the capacity that a human brain has, but
it is getting better. And researchers
are trying to build models of human
beings. At the same time, many
researchers are calling for ethical
oversight because there is virtually
none in this field. This is one of two
companies, Cortical Labs and Final
Spark, that are selling out brain
servers. Yes, lab-grown human brains
that can do computation. There's a
number of reasons why you'd want to do
this.
And you can even use a biological
computer. Yes, a brain organoid
integrated computer. You could have it
at home if you really wanted to. Those
two fields are biomed and computation,
and they are intertwined because you can
use computation to determine what a
brain organoid is doing under different
circumstances, and that is incredibly
valuable to research. For the first time
ever, we have a human model using human
tissue that does not require a human.
And it is significantly more like us
than, say, a mouse, but it still lacks
an integrated system, which is why
people are combining them with other
kinds of organoids. In this one, they
gave brain organoids a miniature spinal
cord. Now, when you communicate with
brain organoids, so if you have them run
a video game, for example, and yes,
people did find that they're capable of
goal-directed learning, which is pretty
much as close to the concept of want or
desire that you could get from an
organoid. But this kind of research
applies to biomed. It's been applied to
things like Alzheimer's because you can
see how they behave and how they're
capable of learning under different
circumstances, and that is a really
great way to find candidate medications.
But so far, that communication has been
limited to electric shocks. They seem to
like ordered electrical signals and
dislike random signals. They don't like
being shocked randomly. But giving them
a sensory pathway that makes them
capable of responding to physical
stimuli is a lot more similar to human
sensation. I mean, let's not sugarcoat
it. It is human sensation.
In this paper, they hooked up a human
brain organoid to a human heart
organoid. A little blob connected to a
blob, but they are able to monitor the
neural pathways between the heart and
the brain. This could be done with any
system. We have the ability to isolate
organs with brains and how they interact
with each other, which is a a huge
advancement and cuts out the middleman.
You are reducing variables. Yes, they
are incredibly valuable tools, and yes,
some researchers have claimed sentience.
That was the organoid Pong one, because
they're capable of learning and growing
and having a preference. So, in terms of
sentience, the capacity to have an
experience, some would say yes, but that
is hotly debated. I mean, just in terms
of intuitive understanding of what a
brain is, they are little blobs. They
are little subunits of what could have
been a brain, but are instead a blob.
Nonetheless, this field is developing
really rapidly, and there are global
efforts to make the best assembloid, to
make the best model of a human being. We
try to weigh potential harm with
potential benefits in science. And
trying to make miniature human beings
has a great potential for harm. We don't
want to deny that these things can have
an experience and find out much later
when we've created much more complex
organoid systems that they're actually
suffering. I also think it's important
to say that I don't think this is how
we're going to get real artificial
intelligence. I mean, we can talk about
quantum, and there's some very cool
papers coming out about scaling that to
a robot.
But for organoids, I think their value
is going to be entirely within biomed.
Maybe they will inform us about the
developing human brain so we can build
better robot brains using synthetic
analog human neurons and crafting that
into a brain that we can get logic out
of.
So, do you think that the ethics changes
if a brain organoid can have a physical
sensation in the way that we do? Or is
that just the same as communicating with
them with electric pulses?
Even if you're on the reductionist side,
it makes me a little bit uncomfortable.